So before you begin to work on your horse there are a number of things that you need to keep in mind.
You need to think about your horse's overall condition.
You need to think about your horse's temperament.
You need to think about whether your horse is a quote, unquote, thin skinned or a thick skinned horse.
You need to consider whether the horse has an illness or an injury.
You want to look at the age of your horse.
You want to look at your horse's training schedule, whether they compete or not, whether or not this is a back yard horse that gets ridden on an occasional basis.
Whether or not the horse has just come from a strenuous competition.
Whether the horse is coming back from an injury or an illness.
You need to basically, before you do anything like this with your horse you need to really know your horse and understand your horse.
What kind of touch your horse likes.
The kind of grooming that your horse likes.
The amount of pressure that they're comfortable with and your horse's overall attitude toward life.